Java Spring Framework specialist

morsor.dk apse:morten@morsor.dkatt: Morten Sorensenw:http://morsor.dkElbagade 22A, 4thm:+45 2225 6945

DK-2300 Copenhagen S

Denmark

VAT number: DK 3069 4384

Born: 1969

Education: M.Sc. Geology, Univ. Copenhagen, 1996

Profile:

When coding, I stress simplicity, transparency and documentation and am acutely aware of the fact that my code must be maintainable and expandable by others with minimum future hassle.

My education and recent career have sharpened my analytical skills, ability to focus and my sense of quality. In addition, my teaching, mentoring and sales experiences have improved my communication skills, especially in dealing with people with vastly different backgrounds.

As a rule, my focus is long-term to ensure future code maintainability. However, I am equally capable of applying a short-term focus to an acute problem, ensuring the problem is solved with minimum damage to the underlying long-term goals.

Because all aspects of analysis, design and coding interest me, I prefer to be involved in all development phases. However, I do not insist in being involved in an area I feel is already adequately addressed.

On projects I tend to oppose the general mood. When the general state is naively optimistic, I play the Devil's Advocate and am critical of the development process, whereas I on 'doom-and-gloom' projects focus on anything at least partially successful and seek to produce actual results to change the mood.

Certifications:

SpringSource Certified Professional Certified Scrum Master Sun Certified Java Programmer Sun Certified Web Component Developer Sun Certified Business Component Developer

Skill	Experience	Last used	1 to 5
Java/JEE			
Java in general	18 years	2023	5
J2EE/JEE	14 years	2023	5
Spring Framework	18 years	2023	5
Spring Boot	5 years	2023	5
Hibernate/JPA	4 years	2023	4
Junit	17 years	2023	4
Apache Tomcat	12 years	2019	4
JBoss	2 years	2015	3
BEA WebLogic	2 years	2014	3
IBM Websphere	1 year	2015	3
Java Server Faces	1 year	2013	3
Grails	1 year	2012	3
Groovy	3 years	2022	3
Apache Camel	1 year	2015	3
Development Tools			
IntelliJ IDEA	15 years	2023	5
Eclipse IDE	5 years	2015	4
Maven	13 years	2023	4
Ant	4 years	2014	4
Gradle	3 years	2023	4
Hudson/Jenkins	11 years	2023	4
Git/Github	10 years	2023	4
Subversion	7 years	2015	4
CVS	3 years	2008	3
Databases			
MySQL	10 years	2017	5
Oracle	6 years	2023	4
MongoDB	1 year	2019	3
PostgreSQL	2 years	2023	4
Microsoft SQL Server	3 years	2010	3
Sybase 1 year	•	3	3
Borland Interbase		2002	2
IBM DB2	1 year	2002	2
Database design	1 year 10 years	2013	4
Web servers			
HTTP in general	14 years	2023	5
_	•	2023	4
Apache	12 years		3
MS IIS	2 years	2007	3

Frontend

Javascript	17 years	2023	4
jQuery	2 years	2014	4
Angular	5 years	2023	4
PHP	8 vears	2010	4

Two PHP-based CMS have been developed and sold

HTML and XML

HTML/XHTML	19 years	2023	5
CSS	12 years	2022	5
XML	6 years	2021	5
XSL/XSLT/Xpath	5 years	2021	5
XMLSchema	3 years	2021	4
DTD	2 years	2021	4

Generally, valid XHTML and valid XML defined by XMLSchema is the goal

Operating systems

Windows (NT -> 10)	23 years	2023	4
Linux (Redhat, Ubuntu)	10 years	2020	4
Mac OS	10 years	2023	4
FreeBSD	2 years	2010	3
Solaris	1 year	2002	2

System administration

Apache web server	12 years	2021	4
Mailserver: Qmail	3 years	2003	3
DNS/BIND	3 years	2004	4
Samba	6 years	2008	4

Languages

5
5
5
4
3
2
1

English skills gained during childhood by attending international schools abroad.

Project experience:

June 2001 - Present morsor.dk (self-employed)

Until 2003 the primary activity was the production, sale and delivery of a file-based CMS, targeting small businesses already having an un-editable website. The system was sold to 12 clients, among them the Copenhagen Central Station shopping center.

In 2003 the focus shifted to consulting paid by the hour, targeting slightly larger companies. The role was often as the client's advisor in relation to their other larger IT-partners and involved participating in meetings, formulating the questions and explaining and evaluating the answers.

Developing and selling my own software has given me considerable experience with finding and keeping customers.

- Developed a file-based CMS in PHP and sold it to 12 clients
- IT-advisor for smaller companies often in relation to their larger partners
- Sales experience and customer contact
- Contractor with larger clients since 2006

October 2022 - May 2023 Copenhagen Business School

Freelance Java systems developer working on integrating external (mostly SAP) systems and an internal Hub, using Java, Spring and Spring Boot.

January 2022 - September 2022 **DXC (at Danish Tax authorities)**

Freelance Java systems developer working on modernizing JSP/Struts-based backend to Spring, REST and React.

August 2021 - December 2021 Bankdata (Danish Financial IT)

Freelance Java systems developer working on backend bank applications based on Java and JAX-RS REST deployed to an OpenShift environment. In addition, some frontend work in Angular.

July 2020 - May 2021 Karnov Group (Danish/Swedish legal publisher)

Freelance developer working on XML-content related tasks, with heavy use of XSLT, XPath, XQuery, XML Schema and DTDs.

April 2020 - June 2020 BEC (Danish bank IT supplier)

Java developer on my previous project, this time concentrating on technical Java-related

upgrades and consolidating the application in the organization. Technically, the application is a Utility tool for configuring SAP Business Objects via a Java API implemented using XML, XSLT and XML Schema.

August 2019 - March 2020 **Nets A/S (Danish payment solutions)**

Freelance systems developer in the Finance and Risk Management department (Anti-Fraud and Disputes) and LCM (Life Cycle Management) creating Spring Boot REST microservices for payment card blocking.

January 2019 - April 2019 Coop (Danish retail)

Java developer working on the client's SAP integration project based on Java 11 with Spring Boot running on a Docker/Kubernetes platform. In addition, some frontend based on Angular, REST and JWT.

September 2017 - December 2018 **BEC (Danish bank IT supplier)**

Java developer working on the client's SAP Business Objects Upgrade project with data migration using SAP's Java interface. Utility tool implemented using XML, XSLT and XML Schema. Later, responsible for development of REST APIs based on Spring Boot in the Real Estate group.

May 2017 - August 2017 IST (IT for schools and daycare)

Java developer working on the client's day-care placement administration webapp based on Java, Spring, Tomcat and Angular.

January 2016 - March 2017 Nordea (Largest Nordic bank)

Java developer working on mobile-oriented services integrating with backend systems. Technology stack based on Java 8, Spring Boot, Spring Security and RxJava.

April 2015 - December 2015 Region Hovedstaden (Danish public health care)

Java developer working on team tasked with integrating 40+ health care systems using Java, Spring and Apache Camel.

November 2014 - March 2015 ATP (Danish Pensions)

AngularJS/Java developer working on modernizing existing IBM/Servlet/JSF webapps hosted at Virk.dk to a more 'responsive' and light-weight frontend based on AngularJS and Bootstrap

January 2014 - September 2014 Nordea, Infrastructure and Operations

Javascript developer working on web-enabling internal applications using Sencha's ExtJS for exposing PL/SQL services via Java JAX-RS

June 2013 - September 2013 **Sophion Bioscience**

Java developer in a medico-technical company producing Swing based software for lab equipment

January 2013 - May 2013 Lequa AB (Malmö, Sweden)

Java-Spring developer working on secure digital interaction software

May 2012 - December 2012 Visma Consulting

Java-Spring developer working on modernizing and simplifying the existing vTrack application used for monitoring large fishing vessels.

- Java, Spring web applications using Spring MVC and jQuery
- Platform: Oracle, Tomcat, Subversion

March 2012 - March 2012 zmags

Short-term contract investigating options regarding upgrading Jenkins/Maven/Subversion build environment

• Java environment with build system based on Jenkins, Maven and Subversion

January 2012 - March 2012 Danish Business Authority

Grails systems developer with Spring/Hibernate skills working on a revamp of the public web-enabled registration of new companies.

- Grails with Groovy based on Spring and Hibernate
- Platform: JBoss, Drools

September 2011 - December 2011 Danish National Board of Industrial Injuries

Java systems developer specializing in the Spring Framework assisting with consolidation and modernization of various older Java services.

- JEE with Spring MVC and Spring Security
- Persistence in JPA using Hibernate against Oracle
- OCES certificate log in
- Platform: Tomcat replacing JBoss

November 2010 – August 2011 **Dibs Payment Services**

Java systems developer specializing in the Spring Framework working on web-enabled payment services.

- Spring MVC with REST and SOAP web services
- Backend in JPA using Hibernate
- Project model was Scrum
- All code subjected to code review

July 2010 - October 2010 **Topdanmark (Danish insurance)**

PHP coder with an object oriented approach for the final months of the B2B project, based on the client's in-house web framework and the open source CMS Typo3.

- Backend consisted of web services running on CICS
- Frontend entirely in PHP using the client's web framework
- Project model was Scrum
- Source code control in Serena Dimensions
- Security in Portal Protect delivered by IT-Practice

April 2010 - June 2010 **Sirius IT**

Hired as a Java-Spring generalist during the final phases of the development of a portal for the Danish Working Environment Authority enabling online registration of workplace accidents.

- Backend based on Spring Framework 3
- Login using certificates from DanID
- Web and service layers secured using Spring Security
- Persistence using JPA annotations and Hibernate (Oracle)
- Frontend in Spring MVC

August 2009 – March 2010 **Siemens**

Java integration project involving bug fixing and adding new features to a support ticket system synchronization application. The application was based on older, procedural Java code, rendering the system virtually unmaintainable. After an initial 3 months of critical bug fixing, I proposed a rewrite using modern object oriented techniques and project management.

The application was rewritten from scratch and based on the Spring Framework, JPA via Hibernate and Spring Integration, with automated testing.

- Code quality improved significantly using well-known design patterns
- Backend based on Spring Framework 3
- Persistence using JPA annotations delegating to Hibernate
- Queue-based system using Spring Integration (Enterprise Integration Patterns)
- Automated unit and integration tests (JUnit, DbUnit, Unitils)
- Old platform (Java 1.3, Tomcat 3 and Axis 1) upgraded to Java 1.6 and the latest Tomcat
- Development environment based on IntelliJ, Maven and automated tests

June – August 2009 Nordic Council of Ministers

Partnership with Cool:Dev developing a new editable website for Baltic Sea Parliamentary Conference.

In addition to improving overall usability by restructuring the website, an administrative backend enabling website management by non-technical staff was created.

- Backend: Grails, built on Spring and Hibernate
- Frontend: Grails using GSP, Sitemesh and YahooUI
- Document indexing: Compass and Lucene
- Development environment: IntelliJ, Jetty, Tomcat

October 2006 – April 2009 YouSee (Danish cable TV provider)

Java frontend developer involved in creating a new customer service system based on Java Server Faces (IceFaces) and Spring in a Weblogic 9.2 environment.

Prior to that, involved in upgrading a Weblogic 8.1 J2EE development environment based on CVS and Ant to WebLogic 9.2 using Subversion and Maven.

Responsible for consolidation of documentation from various sources to a Confluence wiki

and implementing Single Sign On for WebLogic using Active Directory.

- Coded JSF frontend (IceFaces) based on use cases
- Scrum based project with 2 week iterations
- Backend based on EJB and web services deployed on WebLogic
- Development environment: IntelliJ, Maven and Subversion
- Documentation in Confluence instead of Word, Maven sites, HTML
- Single Sign On for WebLogic using Active Directory

January – September 2006 Jyske Bank A/S

Contractor responsible for upgrading the aging HTML of the existing web-based banking application to modern and maintainable HTML.

The project was part of a major corporation-wide layout revamp and the main challenge was implementing a modern layout, while changing the backend COBOL code responsible for generating the HTML as little as possible.

- 100% validating XHTML and as simple as possible CSS and Javascript
- Thorough documentation and adherence to best practices
- Mentoring clients employees
- Considerable contact with bank domain experts
- Cooperation with other departments implementing a similar layout on vastly different Java technology

March - May 2005 ATP Ejendomme A/S (Real estate)

Contractor hired for development of web-based CMS for displaying rentable real estate from a backend database on the corporate website.

- Backend: VB.NET on Windows 2003 Server with SQL Server as database
- Frontend: 100% XML/XSLT
- Integration with client's CMS Synkron
- Testing cross-browser compatibility

June 2004 - February 2005 buyingexperience (e-biz consultancy)

Contractor involved in development and delivery of the client's web-based email campaign management system to external clients.

- Platform: OpenACS (AOLServer on Linux with Tcl for scripting and Oracle as the database) and Qmail mail server
- Considerable client and end-user contact in the Nordic countries
- Testing involved validation of workflow and cross-browser compatibility

March - April 2004 Accord A/S (Record store)

Contactor involved in replacing an existing online auction with a customization of the open source product PHPAuction.

- Client advisor in relation to larger IT-providers
- Identifying auction requirements and finding a suitable platform
- Contact with the online auction provider and the client's other IT-partners
- Working within a very tight budget

March - June 2002 Orion Information Services (mobile content provider)

Contactor assisting in the development of a commercial website combining web-based dating with the cell phone text messaging via SMS.

- Backend: Linux, Apache, PHP with a Borland Interbase database
- Implemented profile administration, mail, profile search and SMS gateway integration
- Project completed under considerable time pressure with vague and ever-changing requirements

June - November 2001 morsor.dk (self-employed)

Developing a Content Management System (CMS) targeted at small businesses – and making the first sale and delivery.

Due to the target segment often having little or no IT experience, the system had to be very intuitive and configurable according to the client's needs. This was achieved by creating links into the CMS using the client's terminology, rather than general CMS terms such as node, folder and group.

- CMS coded in PHP with text files as database
- Flexible regarding website layout and client terminology
- Sold to 12 clients over the following 2 years, among them the Copenhagen Central Station shopping center

March - May 2001 Nordea (Nordic bank)

Employed at IT-Practice as a web developer and testing the client's J2EE-based Internet banking application.

- Testing application flow on various platforms, e.g. Windows (95, 98, ME, 2000) and Macintosh
- Ensuring the SSL certificate worked cross-platform, in addition to resolving the usual cross-platform DHTML problems

November 2000 - February 2001 Nordea (Nordic bank)

Employed at IT-Practice as a web developer and working on the development of the client's J2EE-based secure email application (Solomail).

- Frontend coded in JSP accessing the business logic via Java Beans
- Quite complex browser-neutral DHTML interface with Outlook-like functionality at a time when browsers' DHTML capabilities and implementations were vastly different
- Validating application flow in various browsers, ensuring acceptable performance and verifying correct integration to the under-lying Lotus Notes system

August - October 2000 Pure A/S (Danish internet start-up)

Employed at a now defunct internet startup as a developer focusing on logistics and integration with external partners.

- Responsible for logistics-IT integration
- Platform: OpenACS running on AOLServer with Tcl as the scripting language using Oracle as the database

June - August 2000 Novo Nordisk A/S (Danish medical)

Employed at Framfab as a systems developer and working on the development of a new website including a Java-based CMS for the client.

- Coding Java servlet frontend based on use cases
- Backend: OpenCMS using Oracle as the database

March - May 2000 Kompan (Danish industry)

Employed at Framfab as a systems developer and working on the development of a new website including a CMS for the client.

- Responsible for implementing a website News module
- Platform: Inhouse CMS, Java servlets and Oracle database

September 1999 - February 2000 www.travis.com (Internet plane booking)

Employed at Framfab as a systems developer and working on the initial launch of the online plane ticket booking website for the internet startup company www.travis.com.

- Participated in building a CMS from scratch
- Integration with external plane ticket booking providers
- Platform: Apache and PHP on Solaris with Oracle database
- Tested order-flow, cross-browser issues and performance

January 1999 - August 1999 Copenhagen Fur Center (Fur dealership)

Employed at IBM as a systems developer and working on the development of an extranet of associated mink farmers for online reporting of breeding results.

- Version 1 coded in IBM proprietary Net.Data and Rexx
- More ambitious version 2 based on Java servlets

June 1998 - December 1998 Dyrups (Paint retailer)

Employed at IBM as a systems developer and working on the re-launch of the client's website.

• Creating interactive Java applets integrated with the Lotus Notes backend.

Updated October 2023